<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to A letter from Dr. Bray directed to such as have contributed towards the propagating Christian knowledge in the plantations. By Joseph Wyeth.</title>
            <author>Wyeth, Joseph, 1663-1731.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67210</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3758</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R221264</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99832598</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99832598</idno>
            <idno type="VID">37072</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67210)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 37072)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2105:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to A letter from Dr. Bray directed to such as have contributed towards the propagating Christian knowledge in the plantations. By Joseph Wyeth.</title>
                  <author>Wyeth, Joseph, 1663-1731.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>19, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed and sold by T. Sowle, in White-Hart-Court in Gracious-street,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The letter by Thomas Bray was printed in 1700 (cf. Wing), and was related to missionary work in the colony of Maryland.</note>
                  <note>Copy stained with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bray, Thomas, 1658-1730. --  Letter from Dr. Bray --  Controversial literature --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Missions --  Maryland --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:37072:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:37072:1"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO A LETTER FROM Dr. <hi>BRAY,</hi> Directed to ſuch as have contributed to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Propagating <hi>Chriſtian Knowledge</hi> IN THE PLANTATIONS. By JOSEPH WYETH.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed and Sold by T. <hi>Sowle,</hi> in <hi>White-Hart-Court</hi> in <hi>Gracious-ſtreet,</hi> 1700.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:37072:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
            <pb facs="tcp:37072:2"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" resp="#OXF" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb facs="tcp:37072:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:37072:3"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO A LETTER From Dr.<hi>BRAY.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>BEing one of thoſe who are heartily Deſirous that <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Knowledge</hi> be propageted in the <hi>Plantations,</hi> and have in my ſmall proportion, contributed thereto; I ſuppoſe my ſelf to come within the compaſs of the Doctor's Direction, and as ſuch, have ſome kind of Right to Read and Conſider his Letter, and alſo to Reply to it, upon finding him either <hi>Miſtaken</hi> or <hi>Partial;</hi> and I cannot avoid thinking he is both. <hi>Partial,</hi> in attemptiug to break the common Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty of the people of <hi>Maryland,</hi> for the private Advantage of a few Clergy-men: <hi>Miſtaken,</hi> not only in calling his Attempt by the glorious Title of <hi>Promoting Chriſtian Knowledge,</hi> but alſo, in the Way and Means to effect it; and therefore have given my ſelf the trouble of the following Papers, to contribute yet farther, if it may be, to undeceive any who may be miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by the Doctor's <hi>Letter,</hi> which I ſhall conſider chiefly under two General Heads.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, <hi>With reſpect to the</hi> Deſign.</item>
               <item>Secondly, <hi>The Method by him propoſed to carry on and effect the</hi> Deſign.</item>
            </list>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The <hi>Deſign</hi> it ſelf; The Doctor, p. 1. and in his firſt Paragraph, ſays, <hi>is for the Deſtruction of the Powers of Darkneſs, and the Enlargement of Chriſt's Kingdom in his Majeſty's Planta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:37072:4"/>
            <p>This <hi>Deſign,</hi> when real, and not pretended only, is a <hi>Deſign</hi> ſo Noble, Juſt and Honourable, that it is worthy the hearty Encouragement of all Faithful Chriſtians; and all ſuch can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but think themſelves engaged to Contribute, according to their ſeveral Capacities, for the effecting of it; becauſe, that in the Progreſs of this Work, it makes <hi>Governours</hi> and <hi>Government</hi> Secure and Eaſie; it makes <hi>Families</hi> Sober and Induſtrious; it makes <hi>Societies</hi> Pleaſant and Profitable; in fine, it makes all Happy; by taking from the ſeveral Orders of Men, that irregular Paſſion, which is the ground both of Sin and Strife. But as beſt things, when corrupted, prove the worſe, by adding Malignity to their Degeneracy; ſo the nobleſt of Deſigns may be pretended to cover very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary Intentions: Thus the Doctor, under the ſpecious Pretence of the <hi>Deſtruction of the Powers of Darkneſs,</hi> hath plainly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured the <hi>Deſtruction of the Power of Chriſtian Liberty;</hi> and under the pretence of <hi>Enlarging Chriſt's Kingdom,</hi> hath ſhewn his zealous endeavour for the <hi>Enlarging Anti-ſcriptural Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rarchy,</hi> and <hi>Secular Power,</hi> in the Perſon of the Prieſt; not barely to the prejudice of <hi>Chriſtian Knowledge,</hi> but poſitively againſt the end and deſign of the Goſpel of Peace, which Jeſus Chriſt is the Author of, and which the Apoſtles preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed: And therefore it cannot be unacceptable to every Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributer, to the Advancement of <hi>Chriſtian Knowledge,</hi> to ſee the Fallacy of the Pretence detected; by ſhewing, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of that Excellent Deſign, the bottom is, as the Apoſtle has it, to <hi>ſeek their own, and not the things which are Jeſus Chriſt's.</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Phil. 2. 21.</note>
            </p>
            <p>As to the firſt of theſe, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Deſtruction of the Power of Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> the Doctor has plainly ſhewn his Endeavour and Aim, in theſe words, <q rend="inline">Now that the <hi>Quakers</hi> are openly, and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> more <hi>covertly,</hi> making their utmoſt Efforts <note place="margin">Letter, p. 1. Art. 3.</note> againſt the <hi>Eſtabliſhment of our Church,</hi> by falſe Repreſentations at home, of the Numbers and Riches of their Party; and by inſinuating, that to <hi>Impoſe</hi> upon them an <hi>eſtabliſhed Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance</hi> for the Clergy, would be prejudicial to the Intereſt of the Province, by obliging ſo many weathly Traders to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>move from thence: the Falſity of which, they <hi>(the Clergy)</hi> thought me beſt able to make appear. </q>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:37072:4"/>
            <p>The Apoſtles, when they <hi>eſtabliſhed Churches</hi> in the Faith, they tell us, <hi>They delivered them the Decrees for to keep, that</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 16. 4.</note> 
               <hi>were ordained of the Apoſtles and Elders which were at</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</p>
            <p>Theſe Decrees were few and ſhort; and among them there is no mention of <hi>impoſing</hi> a Maintenance: I will recite them. <hi>It ſeemed good to the Holy Ghost, and to us, to lay upon you</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Acts 16. 28, 19.</note> 
               <hi>no greater Burthen than theſe neceſſary things: That ye abstain from Meats offered to Idols, and from Blood, and from things Strangled, and from Fornication: From which if you keep your ſelves, ye ſhall do well. Fare ye well</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And if the Doctor had ſought the <hi>Establiſhment of his Church,</hi> by the delivering of theſe Decrees, and preſſing with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt Earneſtneſs, the neceſſity of a <hi>Holy Life</hi> he might reſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf moſt firmly aſſured, that the Quakers never did, nor will ever oppoſe ſuch an <hi>Apostolick Establiſhment:</hi> But if the <hi>Esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhment of his Church,</hi> muſt be upon the Ruine of the Temporal Eſtates of thoſe, who agree not with him in Worſhip, in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving that Security, which the Priviledges of their firſt Set<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlements, and the Sanction of a Law, hath given them: He ought not to take it ill, that we openly oppoſe that.</p>
            <p>As for any <hi>Covert</hi> Oppoſition, or any Oppoſition at all made, by Papiſts, to the Doctor's <hi>Eſtabliſhment,</hi> I known of none, nor cannot at preſent find a reaſon why they ſhould diſagree; un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it were upon the Queſtion, Who ſhall be the <hi>Receivers</hi> of the <hi>Maintenance?</hi> But with this I care not now farther to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble my ſelf; but ſhall proceed to ſhew, that this <hi>Chriſtian Liberty,</hi> which the Doctor would now deſtroy, was very earlily provided for, by a Law made in that Province, and confirmed by the Government here, and bears date the 6th of <hi>August,</hi> 1650. which Law is entituled, A Law of Maryland <hi>for Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: In which, among other things, it is ſaid,</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">And where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>as the inforcing the Conſcience, in matters of Religion, hath frequently fallen out to be of dangerous Conſequence, in thoſe <hi>Commonwealths</hi> where it hath been practiſed; and for the more quiet and peaceable Government of this Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince, and the better to preſerve mutual Love and Unity amongſt the Inhabitants here: Be it therefore alſo, by the Lord Proprietary, with the Advice and Aſſent of this Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, Ordained and Enacted, except as in this preſent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:37072:5"/> Act is before declared and for forth, that no Perſon or Perſons, within this Province, or the Iſlands, Ports, Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours, Creeks, or Havens, thereunto belonging, profeſſing to <hi>believe in Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> ſhall not, from henceforth, be any ways troubled, moleſted, or diſcountenanced, for, or in reſpect, of his or her Religion, nor in the free Exerciſe thereof, within this Province, or the Iſlands thereunto be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longing; nor <hi>any way compell'd</hi> to the <hi>Belief</hi> or Exerciſe of any other Religion, againſt his or her Conſent.</q> And af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Clauſe, for the Security of the Civil Government, it goes on, <q rend="inline">And that all, and every Perſon and Perſon, that ſhall preſume, contrary to this Act, and the true Intent and Meaning thereof, directly or indirectly, either in <hi>Perſon</hi> or <hi>Eſtate,</hi> wilfully to Wrong, Diſturb, Trouble or Moleſt, any Perſon or Perſons whatſoever, within this Province, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſing to <hi>belive in Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> for or in reſpect of his or her Religion, or the free Exerciſe thereof, within this Province, otherwiſe than is provided for in this Act, that ſuch Perſon or Perſons, ſo offending, ſhall be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell'd to pay treble Damages to the Party ſo Wronged or Moleſted; &amp;c. </q>
            </p>
            <p>Whoſoever, that is not ſtrangely bigotted to <hi>Perſecution</hi> and <hi>Impoſing,</hi> muſt, upon reading of this <hi>Law,</hi> agree with the Doctor in his Character of the People of <hi>Maryland:</hi> 
               <q rend="inline">They are, ſays he, generally obſerved to be a People of quick <note place="margin">Letter p. 2.</note> Parts, and good Intellectuals.</q> I am ſure, to me, this is an Argument that they are ſo. For in this Law, they ſecured a <hi>Scirpture Belief,</hi> and preſerv'd a Liberty, which the Apoſtle hints at, when he ſays, <hi>Who art thou that judgeſt another Man's Servant? To his own Maſter be ſtandeth or falleth: Yea, he ſhall be</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Rom 14. 4.</note> 
               <hi>holden up: For God is able to make him ſtand.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In this they did very prudently: For hereby all Profeſſors of Chriſtianity ſtood upon the ſame foot of Advantage; none, as Chriſtian, had Power of <hi>Impoſing a Maintenance</hi> from others, each were free to eſtabliſh Churches, and maintain Miniſters (if they would) for themſelves. And if thoſe, who Labour in the Word and Doctrine, Labour in a Goſpel Spirit, and Live according, they need never fear but the People they Labour amongſt will chearfully ſupply their Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſities; for which they have the Promiſe of <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:37072:5"/> if they have Faith enough to depend upon it. But to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed. <hi>This Legal Security,</hi> and ſome other Previous Advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tages, was both Incouragement and Protection for ſome early Planters, to ſettle in that Province; among which, with the Doctor's leave, ſome, not of the Lateſt, nor moſt Inconſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, were <hi>Quakers;</hi> whoſe Chriſtian Sobriety, and Rational Diligence, has been of no ſmall Advantage to the publick Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage of that Province, as well as the increaſing Revenue of this Crown: The firſt, their Ingenuous Neighbours will ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge; and of the laſt, there are ſome Witneſſes here, who alſo are much better Judges than the Doctor, what Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judice, both to the Revenue of this Crown, and the Good of that Province, their removal would be.</p>
            <p>But that I may, if poſible, open the Doctor's Eyes in this Queſtion, I will ſet before them a ſhort Scheme and Eſtimate of that Violation, which has repeatedly been offered to the Priviledges of the Law before-mentioned, and which has been as often refuſed to be Confirm'd by the Government here. In order to which, I muſt firſt acquaint my Reader, That the <hi>Law of</hi> Maryland, <hi>for Religion,</hi> before-mentioned, did continue to be the Peoples common <hi>Land-mark</hi> of Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, from the date of its Confirmation, till <hi>Anno</hi> 1692. at which time ſome, either not liking their common Free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom of Religion, with the reſt of the Inhabitants; or elſe not willing to Maintain ſingly their own Chargeable Clergy, did, with the hepl of the then Governour <hi>Coply,</hi> get an Act, to <hi>Impoſe</hi> upon all others to Maintain them; and was enti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled, <hi>An Act for the Service of Almighty God, and Eſtabliſhment of the Proteſtant Religion,</hi> &amp;c. This was ſent over hither for to be confirmed, but when tender'd to the King and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil for that end, (which was five Years after it was brought over, but was kept Dormant, becauſe that till it was diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>allowed, it had the Force of a Law, and accordingly they made Diſtraints by Vertue of it) it was diſallowed, as con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the <hi>Law of Religion</hi> above cited, and the Repeal ſent over, This did not diſcourage that Party, but that they procur'd another Act, of the ſame Title, and to the ſame purpoſe, and ſent it over to be Confirm'd This alſo the King in Council diſallowed, <hi>Anno.</hi> 1699.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:37072:6"/>
            <p>At the time when this Repeal and Diſallowance was ſent over, Doctor <hi>Bray</hi> alſo went, and did ſo effectually beſtir him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, that with the Aſſiſtance of the Clergy, &amp;c. they, in <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradiction</hi> to the repeated Diſallowance of the King and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cil, to their Law, have again renewed the ſaid Act in Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and have made the Title yet narrower than the two former: They were for the <hi>Eſtabliſhment of the Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;</hi> but this is for the <hi>Eſtabliſhment of Religion in this Province, according to the Church of</hi> England. The firſt, it's true, was the moſt Charitable Title, but yet it ſerv'd to the ſame purpoſe, and was expounded as the laſt.</p>
            <p>In this Law, among other things (after their former Pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terns) it is enacted, <q rend="inline">That for the Incouragement of faithful and able Miniſters, labouring in the Work of the Goſpel, to come and reſide in this Province, inſtead of ſuch <hi>Tythes</hi> uſually in <hi>England,</hi> as aforeſaid, a Tax or Aſſeſſment of 40 l. of <hi>To<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacco per</hi> Poll, be Yearly, and every Year ſucceſſively, levied upon every Taxable Perſon, within each reſpective Pariſh, within this Province. </q>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Taxable Perſons,</hi> is underſtood, all Males of ſixteen Years, and upwards, to ſixty; of white Perſons, and all, both Men and Women, Blacks of the like Ages.</p>
            <p>Now for the drawing of the Scheme and Eſtimate, which I promiſed, I ſhall ſuppoſe (for with reſpect to Number, I can do no more, unleſs I had the Aſſiſtance of the Doctor's <hi>Tabula Prima,</hi> &amp;c. of which more anon) that the Heads of Families, who differ in Worſhip from <hi>Epiſcopacy,</hi> their Children and Servants, both White and Black, which are Taxable, may be in Number 6000. (and I think I am not much miſtaken in this Supputation, becauſe the Doctor, in his <hi>Circular Letter</hi> to the Clergy of <hi>Maryland,</hi> at the end of his piece entituled, <hi>Apoſtolick Charity,</hi> printed this Year 1700. hath theſe words, <hi>Eſpecially the Papiſts and Quakers, which I underſtand are numer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous amongst you;</hi> which intimate, there are others who differ from them, though theſe named may be moſt numerous) the Yearly Aſſeſſment of theſe, at 40 l. of <hi>Tabacco per</hi> Poll, valuing the Tabacco, <hi>communibus annis,</hi> at a Penny a Pound, (tho' ſome Years ſince 1692. it has been double that Price) it amouts to One Thouſand Pound Sterling a Year: Which is no inconſiderable Sum, to be taken and diſtrained Annually,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:37072:6"/> for eight Years, as this has been, on pretence for the <hi>Service of Almighty God,</hi> by colour of Laws diſallowed by Authority.</p>
            <p>But as the Aſſeſſments above-mentioned, of 40 l. of <hi>Tobacco per</hi> Poll, hath been gathered by Laws diſallowed, ſo it is ſome degree of Injuſtice, to conſtrain, even thoſe who owned their Miniſtry, to give them ſuch a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain Portion; which Aſſeſſments being added to the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer, will make up, according to the Information I have, a Sum three times the former; the whole Number of Tax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Perſons being ſuppoſed to be about 24000. by which Computation, 4000 Pounds Sterling a Year, has been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken or diſtrained, for 8 Years, for the Clergy of that Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince. The Total of which Sum is, 32000 Pounds; and the Doctor tells us, there <hi>is but 16 Miniſters,</hi> and <hi>the Churches but lately built, and that to the great Charge of the Governour</hi> Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cholſon, <hi>and the Country.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <table>
                  <row>
                     <cell> </cell>
                     <cell>l.</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>That it has been to their great Charge, is likely very true, for if each of theſe 16 Miniſters had for the paſt 8 Years, 100 <hi>l. per Annum,</hi> that will make the Sum of</cell>
                     <cell>— 12800</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Then for Building Churches, and petty Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pences, if at leaſt it has been ſo expended</cell>
                     <cell>—19200</cell>
                  </row>
                  <row>
                     <cell>Total</cell>
                     <cell>32000</cell>
                  </row>
               </table>
            </p>
            <p>Reader, Is not this a notable Burthen to Intail upon a Country, and a ready way to Cramp the Induſtry of its Inhabitants; and thereby prejudice the Revenue of the Crown?</p>
            <p>Now Doctor, as our King is the common Father of his People, and hath carefully excuted his diſtributive Juſtice, How is it conſiſtent with that, and with the <hi>eſtabliſhed Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viledge</hi> of that Province, to ſeek to draw his Authority to colour the <hi>Violence</hi> of a few, who in their deſire, ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves more bent on the Spoil of their Neighbours, and the enſlaving of the People, than either the <hi>Glory and Service of Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God,</hi> or the <hi>common Good of that Province?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Having ſhewn briefly, that the Doctor's Deſign of <hi>Impoſing,</hi> is quite contrary to the Settlement of that Province, to the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:37072:7"/> Will of this Government, as appears in the <hi>Diſallowances</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned, and to the common Good of the People there.</p>
            <p>I muſt beſtow a few Lines, to ſhew the Inconſiſtency of that Deſign, of <hi>Impoſing,</hi> with the Deſign of Chriſtianity; and which I cannot better begin, than with the Account of our Saviour, who it is ſaid, <hi>In the laſt Day, that great Day of the Feaſt, ſtood, and cried, ſaying, If any Man thirſt, let him come</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Iohn 7. 37.</note> 
               <hi>unto me and drink:</hi> But he did not <hi>Impoſe</hi> it upon any; and as Himſelf did not <hi>Impoſe</hi> upon any, ſo the Precepts which he gave his Apoſtles were agreeable; for in great Simplicity and Poverty he ſent them forth <note n="a" place="margin">Matth. 10. 1. Mar. 6. 7.</note> to Preach the Goſpel; and does particularly obſerve to them, that he <note n="b" place="margin">Matth. 10. 16.</note> 
               <hi>ſent them forth as Sheep in the midſt of Wolves.</hi> But when Men, who pretend to be their Succeſſors, ſhall by Force <hi>Impoſe</hi> upon the People to Maintain them, it is proper to read; <hi>They are ſent forth as Wolves in the midſt of Sheep;</hi> and then, who ſent them is no difficult thing to know. But, as our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt did not <hi>Impoſe</hi> himſelf upon any, neither his Diſciples, ſo they left no Precept that any of their Followers ſhould; and their Examples was of ſo much force in Primitive Times, that at a Synod held in <hi>Ireland,</hi> about the Years 450, or 456. it was ordained, <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Conci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lia,</hi> &amp;c. Hen. Spel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, <hi>tom.</hi> 1. p. 52. Can. 11, 12.</note> 
               <q rend="inline">That neither the Alms of Chriſtians Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>communicated, nor which the Gentiles gave, ſhould be received into the Church.</q> And in times acknowledged to be yet Groſſer, and more Dark, viz. about the Year 600, they had yet retained ſo much of true Chriſtianity in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, if at leaſt we may credit our Hiſtorian, <note n="b" place="margin">Beda lib. 1. c. 25.</note> That <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> and thoſe that came with him, <hi>began</hi> (it had been well if they, and all their Succeſſors, had continued) <hi>to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate the Apoſtolick Life of the Primitive Church.</hi> And he parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly mentions their great <hi>Conſtancy</hi> and Self-denial, ſhew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth in their Lives, the excellency of their Doctrine, that they received neceſſary Food, only from thoſe whom they Taught.</p>
            <p>Theſe few Inſtances are ſufficient to ſhew the Inconſiſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of the Doctor's Pretence to <hi>Apoſtolick Charity,</hi> with <hi>Impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing</hi> a Maintenance; and that his <hi>Deſign</hi> of ſo doing, is contrary to the Goſpel of Chriſt: It was in free Love, and without the expectation or poſſibility of Reward, that our Saviour hath
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:37072:7"/> put us into a Capacity of Salvation, and it is <hi>freely</hi> and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out expectation of Reward from Man: that his Miniſters are the Meſſengers of that Glad tidings: And all thoſe whoſe Commiſſions are of the ſame Tenure with the * Apoſtles, on <note place="margin">Acts 26. 18. 1 Cor. 9. 16.</note> ſuch a <hi>neceſſity</hi> is laid, yea, <hi>Wo</hi> is unto them if they Preach not the Goſpel; they skill not, in ſelling the Gifts of the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt, no more than <hi>Peter</hi> did.</p>
            <p>Thus far, with reſpect to the Doctor's Deſign; and next, to the other General Head, which I propoſed, <hi>viz. The Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thod by him propoſed to carry on and effect that</hi> Deſign; which will fall under a two-fold conſideration; 1 <hi>ſt,</hi> As it reſpects the People of the Province: <hi>2dly,</hi> As it reſpects his Clergy there.</p>
            <p>And firſt, for the Doctor's Method to <hi>Propagate Chriſtian Knowledge,</hi> as it reſpects the People, which I will give in his <note place="margin">Letter p. 1. par. 3.</note> own words, <q rend="inline">By the returns given in (ſays he) upon my <hi>Tabula prima Parochialium inquirendorum,</hi> by which, when they ſhall be all ſent in, I ſhall be inabled to give an account of the Names of all Heads of Families, and of the Religion and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals of every individual Man, Woman and Child, Freeman and Slave, White and Black, throughout <hi>Maryland. </hi>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>This is, it ſeems, the Doctor's <hi>Method</hi> and <hi>Undertaking,</hi> and a very <hi>remarkable</hi> one it is; but I cannot forbear asking him, Whence the Pattern of this his <hi>Tabula prima?</hi> All the Acts of the Apoſtles has nothing like it; they, Holy Men, were not ſo ſolicitous of the Names and Numbers of the People in a Province, as they were, that thoſe who had given up their Names for to be Followers of Chriſt, might in all things Adorn the Goſpel. They planted the Faith in godly Sincerity, and not in the cunning Craftineſs of Men. It's true, the Doctor may have an occaſion for ſuch a Scrutiny, which the Apoſtles had not; for if he ſhould leave any of their Names out of his Number, it may be the loſs of 40 l. of <hi>Tobacco per</hi> Poll; and therefore it is not unlikely, but he will endeavour that his <hi>Tabula</hi> be compleat, as to both their Names and Numbers; but with reſpect to their Morals, it is much if his Tables are not often falſe.</p>
            <p>But further, this <hi>Tabula prima Parochialium Inquirendorum,</hi> of the Doctor's, or (to make it once ſpeak Engliſh) <hi>Firſt Table of Pariſh Inquiries,</hi> ſeems to have ſome affinity with the <hi>Inqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitionem</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:37072:8"/> of the Romaniſts, and to be a Branch of their Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chriſtian Politicks, drawn from the <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Writ by</hi> Meurſius, <hi>and printed</hi> 1635.</note> 
               <hi>Decreta Societatis Jeſu,</hi> by which to draw the People under his Girdle; and that this is not bare Gueſs and Surmiſe only, the Doctor's follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing words do ſhew. <q rend="inline">Becauſe I find (ſays he) there comes un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der my Cognizance, ſeveral very important Caſes to be tried ſpeedily, with Relation to the Clergy and Laity. To deter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine ſeveral of which being of ſo high a Nature, as <hi>Eorgc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of Holy Orders, Polygamy and Inceſt,</hi> I want Inſtructions as to the Manner and Forms of Proceedings; and as it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears to me, have no Power, by my Commiſſion, to give ſuch Sentences as the Nature of the Crimes will require, </q>
            </p>
            <p>Upon which, I cannot but tell the Doctor, that whatſoever Perſon, holding Chriſtian Society, does by wicked and unclean Actions (of which, theſe are ſome of the chief) give occaſion of Scandal and Offence, to the Society he pretends to hold <hi>Church-Memberſhip</hi> with; that Society hath no farther Power warranted in the New Teſtament, than to give Admonition, Reproof or Rebuke, upon the Offender; which, if not followed, by the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment of the Offender, then to caſt out and refuſe ſuch an one their Communion. This is all the Proceſs which the Church can make, it being all that our Saviour directed, and what the Apoſtles did <hi>practiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now I make no doubt, but the Doctor's Commiſſion was full as extenſive as that; but if, through the miſtake of the Clerk who drew it, it had been more narrowly worded, yet Holy Writ, without a <hi>Biſhop's Commiſſion,</hi> is both ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Warrant and Precedent, for all that relates to Church-Memberſhip, and a Separation from it: So that had the Doctor deſign'd to govern himſelf in his pretended <hi>Spiritual Function,</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction,</hi> by that <hi>Rule,</hi> he could not want any neceſſary Inſtruction, relating to the manner of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings againſt Sinners of his Communion. But it ſeems it is ſomething more that he wants, <hi>viz. To give ſuch Sentences as the Nature of Polygamy and Inceſt do require.</hi> The Doctor does well to tread ſoftly here, and ſee that his Power be full before he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe the office of the Civil Magiſtrate, and venture to give ſuch Sentences as the Nature of theſe Crimes require, leſt he incur a <hi>Premunire;</hi> for who knows not that theſe Crimes are in their <hi>Nature</hi> juſtly deemed Capital, and the <hi>Sentences,</hi> which our
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:37072:8"/> Laws have provided for them, are according. Here the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor's Commiſſion was <hi>ſhort,</hi> he might <hi>Excommunicate,</hi> but not <hi>Hang</hi> the wicked, and it is like it will be no ſhort while before the <hi>Government</hi> put into his hands ſuch a branch of the Civil Power.</p>
            <p>What I have yet ſaid, has not been with reſpect to <hi>Forgery of Holy Orders,</hi> which the Doctor ſays, does alſo come under his Cognizance; therefore now a word or two of that, and then I have done with theſe great Crimes of ſome of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor's Communicants. It is nothing ſtrange, that the Doctor ſhould want Inſtruction in this matter, becauſe it is a thing not named in all the New Teſtament; and therefore he can have no light, as to the manner of Proceeding, or Sentence from thence againſt it: The neareſt Parallel which the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor can urge from thence, is, where the Apoſtle tells of ſome <hi>that were falſe Apoſtles;</hi> and the mark by which he judged <note place="margin">2 Cor. 11. 13.</note> them to be ſo, was, they were <hi>Deceitful workers:</hi> Now if the Doctor will make this the <hi>Line</hi> and <hi>Rule</hi> of his Judgment, it is too likely he will find no ſmall part of his few Clergy there to be guilty.</p>
            <p>But now, the <hi>deceitful Works,</hi> by which <hi>falſe Apoſtles</hi> were known, cou'd not be the <hi>forging of any Writing or Warrant</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Hand and Seal of a Biſhop, to Uſe and Practiſe as a Miniſter in the Church of Chriſt: Becauſe we read not, that any of the Miniſters of Chriſt had any ſuch thing; ſo much the contrary, that one of the moſt Eminent ſays, <hi>I neither received it of Man, neither was I taught it, but by the Revelation</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Gal. 1. 12.</note> 
               <hi>of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> This was <hi>Holy Orders,</hi> properly and truly ſpeaking. And I deny the Doctor to prove by any War<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant or Authority from Chriſt or his Apoſtles, that That manner of <hi>Ordination</hi> and <hi>Miſſion</hi> is now ceaſed; and that it is now meerly Humane and Political, according to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Practiſe of Chriſtendom. This brings me to the <hi>2d</hi> Conſideration of the Doctor's Method, as it reſpects his Clergy there: In the Choice of which, that are now to be ſent over, the Doctor ſeems to be very careful, when he ſays, <hi>He would have them to be of a true publick diſintereſted, <note place="margin">Letter. p. 2. Par. 6.</note> in one word, of a miſſionary Spirit.</hi> Theſe will indeed be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Qualifications; becauſe the Man who is truly of a <hi>Miſſionary Spirit,</hi> will find like preſſing neceſſity to Preach the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:37072:9"/> Goſpel, as the Apoſtle ſays he had. And if the Doctor will take only ſuch, inſtead of Thirty, which he ſays he ſhall <note place="margin">1 Cor. 9. 16.</note> at leaſt want, I wou'd be glad, with my whole Heart, if the number were much increaſed; nor wou'd the People be in any danger from them, becauſe ſuch would in Truth and Sincerity ſay, <hi>We ſeek not yours, but you:</hi> And therein give full proof, that they were both <hi>publick Spirited,</hi> and <hi>Diſintereſted</hi> to wordly Things.</p>
            <p>But alas, the Proviſion which the Doctor has ſo carefully began to make, of <hi>Glebes</hi> and <hi>Parſonage-Houſes,</hi> and <hi>Yearly Aſſeſſments</hi> for <hi>Tithes,</hi> are plain Indications to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary of his pretence of <hi>Diſintereſtedneſs,</hi> and ſpeak this no leſs loudly, than <hi>the Bleating of the Sheep, and the Lowing</hi> 
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 15. 14.</note> 
               <hi>of the Oxen,</hi> did <hi>Saul's</hi> Diſobedience.</p>
            <p>That this may appear yet a little plainer, if poſſible, I ſhall obſerve, that the Doctor, in his <hi>General view of the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Colonies</hi> (which is at the beginning of his Piece, <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolick Charity, &amp;c.</hi> printed this Year 1700.) ſays, There are 16 Miniſters in <hi>Maryland;</hi> and in his Letter, as above-quoted, he ſays, He ſhall want at leaſt Thirty, ſo that theſe will make Forty Six in Number, which will be a pretty charge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Company to the Province, by that time they are fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh'd to the Doctor's Mind; for he ſays, <q rend="inline">Fifty Pounds worth of Books being the <hi>leaſt</hi> that can be ſuppoſed re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite <note place="margin">Apoſt. Cha. P. 7.</note> to enable a Miniſter to diſcharge the Duties of his Function.</q> Here the Doctor has taken a Method to ſpend Two Thouſand Three Hundred Pounds, of the Peoples Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, only to help qualifie the Prieſts: Is not that very hard upon the People? Who muſt be obliged to lay out their Money to Teach the Prieſt <hi>gratis?</hi> Yet, when he has learn'd, he will not Teach the People <hi>gratis,</hi> but make them pay for what he takes out of Books which they gave him. If the Doctor can reconcile this to the practiſe of the Primitive Preachers, recorded in the New Teſtament, then we may ſay, He has turn'd over them leaves to ſome purpoſe. But not to inſiſt long on this, I will ſhew how the Doctor does further ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plain himſelf in his <hi>Propoſals for the Encouragement and Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of Religion,</hi> &amp;c. printed in his <hi>Apoſtolick Charity,</hi> before-quoted; <q rend="inline">The Clergy (ſays he) that are already in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:37072:9"/> Plantations, as well as thoſe who are to be ſent thither, cannot (Humanely Speaking) be ſo capable of Informing themſelves, and of Inſtructing others, in the Deſign of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity, in the Nature of the Covenant of Grace, in the Meanings and Importance of the Articles of our moſt Holy Faith, and in the Nature and Extent of all Chriſtian Duties, without the aſſiſtance of ſome good Commentators upon the Holy Scripture. </q>
            </p>
            <p>I muſt not omit here, to obſerve to the Doctor, that if the Clergy which are already in the Plantations, and thoſe who are to be ſent thither, are truly of a <hi>Miſſionary Spirit, having a Zeal for God's Glory, and the Salvation of Mens Souls,</hi> it is impoſſible they ſhould be Ignorant of any Eſſential Part of the Chriſtian Religion: And therefore, if they recur to <hi>Humane Means,</hi> to make themſelves <hi>Goſpel-Miniſters,</hi> they will yet want a <hi>Goſpel Spirit;</hi> and then wonder not, if they ſucceed not in bringing Souls to God: For the turning People from <hi>Darkneſs to Light, and from the Power of Satan to the Power of God,</hi> is only to be done by ſuch, who have firſt known ſomething of the Power of God, to turn them from Satan's Power, by which theſe are both <hi>Miniſters</hi> and <hi>Witneſſes</hi> of thoſe things, in which the Power of Chriſt hath appeared; and theſe will more effectually know <hi>the Deſign of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, in the Nature of the Covenant of Grace,</hi> as it hath wrought in them, than any Commentator whatſoever can teach them. But ſince the Doctor does place ſo eminent a part of his Clergy's Qualifications, in their Acquaintance with good <hi>Commentators,</hi> it may not be amiſs a little to examine the Pretence, and which might have been done with more certainty, had the Doctor named thoſe <hi>good Commentators</hi> he intends; but it will, however, be no very difficult matter to judge, which may be ſome that are ranked in that Number: For when Perſons are diſtinguiſhed by the Epithers of <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers</hi> and <hi>Holy,</hi> there can be no doubt, but theſe, if they have writ Commentaries, they obtain the firſt place; and of ſuch there are very many: Yet that I may not tire my Reader, with too great Variety of them, I will chooſe to Inſtance, particularly, <hi>Hierom,</hi> of whom it is ſaid, <hi>He was</hi> 
               <note place="margin">Daile's vſe of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, lib. 1. p. 112.</note> 
               <hi>the greateſt Critick of them all; and who, by often exerciſing the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:37072:10"/> Strength of his admirable Wit, both by himſelf, and with others, hath obſerved more, touching the Stile, Method, natural Diſpoſition and Opinions of the Fathers, than any other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Man, in an Apology which he writ, ſaith, <q rend="inline">This is the uſual manner of Commentaries, and the Rule that <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Apol. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ.</hi> Ruff. Daile lib. 1. p. 101.</note> Commentators go by; to ſet down in their Expoſitions, the ſeveral Opinions they have met withal; and to deliver both what their own, and what the Judgment of others is upon the place. And this is the Practice, not only of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreters of the Scriptures, but of the Expoſitors alſo, of all kind of Secular Learning, as well in the Greek, as in the Latin Tongue. </q>
            </p>
            <p>Now Doctor, with what certainty, <hi>Humanely Speaking,</hi> can any of thy Clergy learn, from ſuch an undiſtinguiſhed Mixture of Opinions, the <hi>Deſign of Chriſtianity in the Nature of the Covenant of Grace?</hi> But to carry the difficulty, or rather impoſſibility, to its proper length, let us hear the ſame <hi>Hie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rom,</hi> in an Epiſtle which he writ, where, after having named the Writings of <hi>Origen, Didymus, Apollinaris, Theodorus, Heraolas, Euſebius Emiſſenus, Alexander</hi> the Heretick, with others, he ſays, <q rend="inline">That I may therefore plainly tell the Truth, I confeſs, <note place="margin">Hierom <hi>ep. ad</hi> Auguſt. <hi>qu. e eſt 89.</hi> Daile lib. 1. p. 104, 105.</note> that I have read all theſe Authors, and collecting together as much as I could in my Memory, I preſently called for a Scribe, to whom I dictated either my own Conceptions, or thoſe of other Men, without remembring either the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, or the Words ſometimes, or the Senſe. </q>
            </p>
            <p>See here what great Uncertainty the Man is brought into, who ſeeks to them for Information in the <hi>Deſign of Chriſtianity;</hi> while he is reading, as he thinks, <hi>Hierom,</hi> or others of the Fathers (as they are called) it may not be the Opinion of the Man, under whoſe it is found; and how ſhould the Reader know this, unleſs he takes the Advice which <hi>Hierom</hi> gives to <hi>Auguſtine?</hi> Saying, <q rend="inline">If therefore thou lightedeſt upon any thing in my Expoſition, which was worthy of Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſion, it would have ſtood better with thy Learning to have conſulted the Greek Authors themſelves, and to have ſeen whether what I have written be to be found in them, or not; and if not, then to have condemned it as my own private Opinion.</q> See Doctor, where Commentaries lead;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:37072:10"/> for, according to this Advice, each of the Clergy Men ought to have all the Greek Authors; and poſſibly, according to another Man's Advice, they ought to have all the Latine's; by which time the Libraries for thy 46 Clergy-men will coſt near half ſo many Thouſand Pounds: And after all the Expenſe, are not ſuch Comments excellent means to Teach the Clergy, that are to Teach the People? And yet ſuch is the Aſſiſtance that is to be expected from them; for if ſome others have <note place="margin">Daile's <hi>vſe of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, lib.</hi> 1. P. 104.</note> not ſpoke out ſo much, they have done no leſs; witneſs <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lary, Ambroſe,</hi> and others, who Robbing poor <hi>Origen</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Mercy, do not yet do him the Honour, ſo much as to name him ſcarcely.</p>
            <p>What I have ſaid, does only reſpect their <hi>Manner</hi> of wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Commentaries; for as to the <hi>Matter</hi> of them, it falls under a diſtinct Conſideration, wherein, in very great varie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Inſtances it might be ſhewn, that their Opinions are as odd and extravagant, as the manner of Collecting them was precarious, which I deſire not now to trouble my Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der with.</p>
            <p>What I have ſaid, as to the manner of Writing <hi>Commenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries,</hi> may ſerve to ſhew, that, <hi>Humanely Speaking,</hi> they are not proper Aſſiſtances to Teach a Man, <hi>the Deſign of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity, in the Nature of the Covenant of Grace.</hi> But indeed, why ſhould any Man go to look for that in Commentaries, which he may much more plainly, and with infinite more certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, find in Holy Writ, if he bring with him but a fitting Diſpoſition to receive Information, I mean, Sincerity and Humility. Chriſtian Religion, is a plain Religion, its <hi>Deſign</hi> is the Salvation of Men; and there being very many, whoſe Capacities and Underſtandings are not fitted to apprehend nice Subtilties, whoſe Souls are ſtill in the ſame Capacity of Salvation with the Wiſeſt: God, in his Juſtice, has not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>held, even from theſe, a poſſibility of knowing certainly their Duty, and ſufficient Aſſiſtance, whereby they may be enabled to do it; <hi>For the Grace of God has appeared unto all Men,</hi> to teach them both their negative and poſitive Duty, what to leave undone, and what to do; and why any ſhould refuſe this, and depend on them who pore upon <hi>Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries,</hi> and neglect this certain Teacher, I ſee not a Reaſon.</p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:37072:11"/>
            <p>I have now done with the Doctor's <hi>Method</hi> of propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting <hi>Chriſtian Knowledge,</hi> for the preſent, and come to an Aſſertion of his; <q rend="inline">At <hi>Philadelphia</hi> in <hi>Penſibvania,</hi> the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation of Church people, which amounted but to Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty <note place="margin">Letter p. 3. Par. Laſt.</note> or Thirty, at moſt, not two Years ago, through the Bleſſing of God, upon the endeavours of a late <hi>Miſſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary,</hi> is now increaſed, chiefty from Quaker-Converts, to upwards of Seven Hundred. </q>
            </p>
            <p>The Doctor was either foully impoſed upon, or did wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly miſtake the State of the Communicants of his Church in <hi>Penſilvania,</hi> when he ventured to aſſert as above; and I do tell him, that if his <hi>Tables of Pariſh Inquiries</hi> are made with no greater exactneſs, they will not be fit to be de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended upon: For he is very much out both in the Rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion he has given of what the Number of them was, and is; but to me that is not material; for if they were many-fold what he ſays they are, I ſhould by no means be offended, while they were good <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> walking anſwerable to that Holy profeſſion: But when he Inſults and ſays, That they are now upwards of Seven Hundred, chiefly from Quaker-Converts: I muſt put him to rights ſo far, as to tell him, That there is not <hi>Twenty Quaker-Converts</hi> among them; and even of them, I ſuppoſe, he will neither care to give the World a true Account of their Names nor Morals.</p>
            <p>I ſhall now come to the Concluſion, and take leave of the Doctor for this time, when I have taken a little notice of his Liberality, in beſtowing upon G. K. the Epithet, <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent,</hi> and the occaſion of it, when he ſays, <hi>The Feild is there, and the neighbouring Parts, ſo happily Sown by the Excellent Mr.</hi> Keith.</p>
            <p>And firſt, for the occaſion of it, <hi>viz.</hi> The <hi>Field's</hi> being <hi>Sown</hi> by him: Prithee Doctor, What is the Seed, <hi>Tares</hi> or <hi>Wheat?</hi> I am inform'd it is not, nay, I am ſure it cannot be the laſt, if at leaſt he hath Sown the ſame, he is Sowing up and down this Kingdom, ſince his being denied by us, ſuch as Uncharitablencſs, Strife, Contention, Diviſion, and the like; from the Sowing whereof, there can Spring no good Crop: Nor will he prove more than a weak and ſhort Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port to them that depend upon him.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:37072:11"/>
            <p>But ſince the Doctor ſeems to be a Stranger to all this, and therein unacquainted with the true Character of his <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Mr.</hi> Keith, I will preſent him with his ſhort Deſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, in the following Abſtract.</p>
            <p>G. K. is a Man of an unſtable Mind, neither conſiſtent long with himſelf, agreeing with others; by which natural Diſpoſition, and the help of his Eleemoſynary Learning, he accuſtoms his Pen to Scribbling; in which he Perverts Mens Words, Miſrepreſents their Principles, and then draws falſe and odious Conſequences from them; and charges them on thoſe, whoſe Principles, fairly ſtated, do not admit of ſuch undue Concluſions. He hath traduced both the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and the Dead, and by what he writes, he hath ſhewn, that to gratifie his Revenge, he regards not what he ſays, nor what he writes, if he can but expoſe them to Contempt and Reproach, with whom he is Angry. He is one of the greateſt Inſtances of Inconſtancy, Contradiction and Cenſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riouſneſs, which this Age has produced. In a word, He is the Compound of Abuſe and Slander; He is at preſent an Itinerant Preacher, but gaping after ſomething better than that Fatigue; which advance, if he miſs of, <hi>Caveat Hierar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Doctor, This is thy Excellent Mr. <hi>Keith,</hi> in whom, it ſeems, thou art not leſs miſtaken, than in the foregoing parts of thy Letter; all which may'ſt thou amend in thy next, by endeavouring to propagate <hi>Chriſtian Knowledge,</hi> in a Chriſtian Spirit, and by Chriſtian Means,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Is the Deſire of thy Faithful Friend, Joſeph Wyeth.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:37072:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
